Guide to the Robert Schmertz Collection, 1898-2001 CAM.SCHM.2015
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Robert Schmertz Collection
1898-2001
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Schmertz, Robert (Robert Watson)
CAM.SCHM.2015
8 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Robert Schmertz collection is comprised of instruments, posters and programs, music manuscripts, published scores, songbooks, and sound recordings related to the Architect and composer's career.
Biography
Robert Watson Schmertz was born in the Pittsburgh neighborhood of Squirrel Hill in 1898. He was the grandson of Robert Schmertz, the owner of Schmertz & Company, the Duquesne Glass Works and a director of the Pittsburgh Bank For Savings in the late 1800's.
Robert found his musical inspiration when the clan Schmertz would gather for family orchestras, a sort of inter-generational hootenanny where he would sing and strum the banjo with the kin. The banjo was copacetic; someone left it at the house and young Schmertz, who had never played an instrument, picked it up. Little did he know then where that long-necked, five-string banjo would lead him.
Schmertz went to Peabody High School, where he first met his wife, Mildred. He then enrolled at Carnegie Tech (now CMU), where he was part of its first school of architecture class and co-wrote the Tartan spirit song "Fight for the Glory of Carnegie."
Robert and Mildred had a son and two daughters: John, Mildred, and Gretchen.
Schmertz taught as a professor for 35 years in the School of Architecture at Carnegie Tech and operated a thriving private practice out of the Seventh Avenue Century Building in town, a few short blocks from where his grandfather ran his business.
He planned the construction of St. Michael's of the Valley Church in Rector, Mt. Lebanon Presbyterian Church's Education Building, Morewood Gardens in Oakland, the renovation of Latrobe's Unity Chapel and was part of the Saxonburg Cyclotron design team (it closed in 1969; it was a nuclear lab campus for Carnegie Tech, complete with its own atom-smasher, that was situated at the spot where KDKA once broadcast) among his many projects. He also designed homes for several prominent local families during his career.
His reputation as a composer and folk performer spread by word-of-mouth beyond the city, with many of his tunes based on Pittsburgh's own lore. It took years for his friends to convince Schmertz to get his music on vinyl. In 1949 a group of friends donated money and bought Schmertz recording time at a local studio. The resulting 78 LP was only pressed 300 times, but had a big influence.
People in folk circles likened him to a contemporary Stephen Foster, and his earthy lyrics won him the title of "Troubadour of the Two by Four." None other than Pete Seeger recalled that "Bob Schmertz was a very good songwriter."
Sometimes derivative in his music, his writing was a brilliant example of the genre. He could rhyme any couplet, keep the words in appropriate dialect and make them flow off a singer's tongue. Telling a simple folk story through song was his forte, and not one easily mastered.
Pete Seeger recorded "Monongahela Sal," a song Schmertz had written in 1947, on the "Story Songs" album from 1961. Burl Ives, Tennessee Ernie Ford, The Statler Brothers and Gary Crosby all recorded versions of "Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord." Ives was a particular fan of Schmertz, recording his "Angus MacFergus MacTavish Dundee," "The Lock Tenders Lament," and "Quack Quack Paddle-Oh." Local folkies The NewLanders included "Monongahela Sal" on their 2003 CD "Where the Allegheny Flows."
But Seeger is the guy who shined the spotlight on Bob Schmertz. Beside "Sal," he played other Schmertz compositions all around America, and always credited the writer. He wasn't alone; every folkie that came through the City visited and often played alongside Schmertz.
Seeger appeared with the American Wind Symphony in the early sixties, performing from their floating stage "Point Counterpoint," which was moored at Point State Park. He brought Schmertz on stage to join him in singing "Monongahela Sal" and several other songs.
But most of Schmertz's performances were at small stages and often concluded in the wee hours at local homes after the gig. He also collaborated with Chatham College's Viv Richman, who recorded 1959's "Vivien Richman Sings Folk Songs of Western Pennsylvania," a Smithsonian Folkways release.
Schmertz did eventually give up his studio shyness in his later years. He recorded three more albums, 1955's "Robert Schmertz Sings His Songs," 1959's "Sing Oh! the City Oh!: Songs of Early Pittsburgh," and 1960's "Ladies Beware of an Architect: Songs for Architects and Their Girlfriends."
His first real LP, "RS Sings His Songs," was a George Heid Productions disc, assisted by Carnegie Tech. It included a couple of his better known songs, "Monongahela Sal" and "Angus MacFergus MacTavish Dundee," among its thirteen tracks.
The album "Songs of Early Pittsburgh," is a collection of tunes Schmertz wrote to celebrate Pittsburgh's 200th birthday bash. The songs featured the rock stars of pre-revolutionary Western PA like George Washington, Christopher Gist, General John Forbes and Seneca Queen Aliquippa. Some of its other tracks were "La Vierge de la Belle Riviere," "Flintlock Finnegan," and "The Prettiest Girl in Pittsburgh Town." This LP is the only one of his works to make a transition from vinyl, reissued as a CD by the Smithsonian Folkways label.
His final "Ladies Beware" was a tongue-in cheek sort of release, and was distributed by the Pittsburgh Architectural Club during its 70th anniversary. It had tunes commemorating Frank Lloyd Wright, IM Pei and Lorenzo Di Medici, along with "The Doric Column Is Coming Back," "Industrious Carpenter Dan" and "Queen Anne's Front" that played to the whimsy of the blueprint set.
He also authored "A Picture Book of Songs and Ballads." That's all the body of work that Bob Schmertz, who passed away in 1975, has left behind.
Additional Schmertz-related material may be found at CMU's Ryan Library as part of the school's architectural archives.
http://oldmonmusic.blogspot.com/2012/05/bob-schmertz-banjo-folklorist.html
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions in this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Robert Schmertz Collection was donated to the Center for American Music in 2000 by Schmertz's daughter, Gretchen Schmertz-Jacobs. Additional items were collected by the Center related to Schmertz-Jacobs death and subsequent memorial service.
Scope and Content Notes
The Robert Schmertz Collection contains instruments, concert posters and programs, music manuscripts, published scores, songbooks, photos, and sound recordings of Schmertz' own performances and those of the major recording artists who recorded his works, including Burl Ives and Pete Seeger.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following 11 series:
Series I. Instruments
Series II. Concert Posters and Programs
Series III. Music Manuscripts
Series IV. Published Scores
Series V. Poems
Series VI. Plays
Series VII. Photographs
Series VIII. Newsclippings
Series IX. Songbooks
Series X. Sound Recordings
Series XI. Miscellaneous
Sheet music; Music -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Music -- Manuscripts; Music -- 20th century; Composers -- United States; Architects -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Carnegie Institute of Technology.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Schmertz, Robert (Robert Watson)
- Instruments, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains Robert Schmertz banjo and mutiple banjo covers that have been autographed by people he played with over the years.
  - Banjo covers, autographed (Box 1, Item 1-3)
  - Schmertz Banjo with case (Box 1, Other Banjo Case 1, Item 1)
- Concert Posters and Programs, II.
  This series contains posters and programs related do Schmertz's public performances.
  - Concert Poster: An Evening of Folk songs by Pete Seeger's "Favorite Songwriter" Robert Schmertz & His Friends, April 12, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Concert Poster: An evening of Pittsburgh's finest folk music with the friends of Robert Schmertz, April 10, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - River City Brass Band Present Appalachian Spring Music from the Easter Mountains, April 28, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Concert program. 6 pages.
  - Lord, I've Got Some Singing to do", May 3, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Program for QED Children's Festival Chorus performance.
  - The Tiffany Concert Series, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Program for concert series by the Allegheny Historic Preservation Society.
  - An Evening of Pittsburgh's Finest Folk Music with the Friends of Robert Schmertz, April 10, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 204)
    Poster advertising a Hootenanny at the Carnegie Lecture Hall, Oakland. Brown cardboard with black screen printing. Correction made in marker.
  - In Loving and Joyous Memory, 1927-2001 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    Program for A Celebration of Gretchen Schmertz Jacob, September 16, 2001, Hazlett Theater.
- Music Manuscripts, III.
  This series contains manuscripts of Schmertz authored songs written in his hand.
  - Aardvark (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Music manuscript. 1 page.
  - Chandu (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Music manuscript. Ink on paper. 4 pages. Written by Robert Schmertz and Matthew W. Frey.
  - Cousin Althea (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dogwood Hollow (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - My Sweetheart Wears the Plaid (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Music manuscript. 3 pages.
  - My Wild Irish Rose is Wilder than She Used to Be (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Music Manuscript. 3 pages. Words by Robert Schmertz. Music by Robert Schmertz and Adolph Herzberg.
  - Dumbella 1st violin arrangement (Box 3, Folder 17)
    music manuscript. 1 page.
  - If you Would be a Sailor's Wife arranged for 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 18)
    music manuscript. 1 page. arranged by J.L. Rosen.
  - In Barcelona 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Nicest Girl arranged for 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Music manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Old Place arranged for 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Ship Ahoy! arranged for 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Moonlight Maid arranged for 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 49 Angels (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Music manuscript. 2 pages. 2 copies (one on photostat).
  - Braddock's Defeat (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Music manuscript. 2 pages. Arranged by Frank C. Jarema.
  - Flintlock Finnegan (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ohio Company (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Music pages. 4 pages. Arranged by Frank C. Jarema.
  - Never Touch Water (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Never Touch Water (front) Dogwood Hollow (back) (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Music manuscripts. 1 page each song. Arranged by Frank C. Jarema.
  - Piney Mountain (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Prettiest Girl in Pittsburgh Town (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - There's No One I Care for but you flute arrangement (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Open the Doors of Delight (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Music manuscript. 4 pages. Words by Robert Schmertz, Music by Robert Schmertz and Adolph Herzberg.
  - There's No One I Care for But You arranged for 1st violin (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Music manuscript. 2 pages. Arranged by J.L. Rosen.
  - Davy Jones arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Dumbella arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - In Barcelona arranged for flutre (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Nicest Girl arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Old Place arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Ship Ahoy arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Toreador arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - We are the Villain arranged for flute (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - 49 Angels (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Raggedy Annie (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Verse to "Night Time in Lime House" (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Limehouse Rose (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Music manuscript. 3 pages. Words by Robert Schmertz. Music by Matthew Frey.
  - You Can't Hold Them (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Music manuscript. 4 pages. Words by Robert Schmertz. Music by Robert Schmertz and Adolph Herzberg.
  - In the Rain (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Winston, Franklin, and Joe (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Music manuscript. 5 pages. Words by Robert Schmertz, music by Paul B. Dickey.
  - Spring on Campus (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Music manuscript. 4 pages.
  - The Lady of the Cloisonne (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Chandu, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Music manuscript. 4 pages. By Robert Schmertz and Matthew Frey. Manuscript in Matthew Frey's handwriting.
  - I'm Going Back to My Baby Eskimo (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Music manuscripts. 4 pages.
  - Ballaugh Mac Lou Mac Lee (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Typed manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Braddock's Defeat (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Celeron (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Typed manuscript. 4 pages.
  - Flintlock Finnegan (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - General John Forbes (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - La Vierge De La Belle Rivere (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Merry Madcap Moskowitz (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Prettiest Girl in Pittsburgh Town (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Quack, Quack, Paddle-O (Box 4, Folder 62)
    Typed manuscript. 3 pages.
  - Sing Oh! The City Oh! (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Singin' Hallelujah (Box 4, Folder 64)
    Typed manuscript. 2 page.
  - Swing Away Pearly Gates (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - The Battle of Bushy Run (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - The Lips that Touches Saxophones (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - The Ohio Company (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - The Old White Bones of Christopher Wren (Box 4, Folder 69)
    Typed manuscript. Three pages.
  - When I was a Young Nouveau (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - When that Architect Comes to Jordan (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Quack, Quack, Paddle-O (Box 4, Folder 73)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript. 3 pages.
  - Mon Petit Lapin (Box 4, Folder 74)
    Music manuscript. 10 pages. Arranged by Frank C. Jarema.
  - General John (Box 4, Folder 75)
    Music manuscript. 1 page. Typed and handwritten.
  - Billows of Pillows with You (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Chang Fu (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Nelly Gwyn (Box 4, Folder 78)
    Typescript of lyrics with handwritten notation on onion skin paper.
  - Swing Away Pearly Gates (Box 4, Folder 86)
    Typed manuscript. Multiple copies.
  - Little Lost Angel (Box 4, Folder 87)
    Typed photocopies of music manuscript.
  - Ballaugh McLou McLee (Box 4, Folder 88)
    typed manuscript.
  - Elephants Never Forget (Box 4, Folder 89)
    Photocopy of typed music manuscript.
  - Flintlock Finnegan (Box 4, Folder 90)
    Photocopy of typed music manuscript. 4 pages.
  - Jose the Horse (Box 4, Folder 91)
    Typed music manuscript. 3 pages.
  - Penny the Pennyguin (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Prettiest Girl in Pittsburgh Town (Box 4, Folder 93)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript. 2 pages. 3 copies.
  - Ralphy the Laughing Giraffe (Box 4, Folder 94)
    typed manuscript. 2 page.
  - Sarah the Slippery Seal (Box 4, Folder 95)
    Photocopy of typed music manuscript. 3 pages.
  - Sing Oh! The City Oh! (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Singing Hallelujah (Box 4, Folder 97)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript.
  - The Knight of Small Renown (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - The Old White Bones of Christopher Wren (Box 4, Folder 99)
    Typed music manuscript. 2 pages.
  - The Rambling River Line (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - When I was a Young Nouveau (Box 4, Folder 101)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript. 4 pages.
  - When I was a Young Nouveau (Box 4, Folder 102)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript with guitar chords. 4 pages.
  - When the Architect Comes to Jordan (Box 4, Folder 103)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript. 2 pages.
  - At the Forks of the Ohio (Box 4, Item 104)
    typed and handwritten manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Oh, Lonely Grenadier (Box 4, Folder 105)
    typed and handwritten manuscript. 1 page.
  - Open Up Those Doors of Delight! (Box 5, Folder 156)
    Title page only. Words by Robert Schmertz. Music by Adolph Herzberg and Robert Schmertz.
  - "Broadway's Rotary Now!" (Box 5, Folder 162)
    copy of handwritten manuscript. 4 pages. Words by Robert Schmertz. Music by Robert Schmertz and Adolphe Herzberg.
  - Josh! (Box 5, Folder 164)
    copy of handwritten song lyrics on lined paper. 6 copies.
  - [Birthday Song] (Box 5, Folder 167)
    Music "Pretty Red Wing"; wordy by Bob Schertz. Typed manuscript of song, front and back.
  - The Rambling River Time (Box 5, Folder 168)
    handwritten manuscript on card stock.
  - Miscellaneous Songs (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Nellie of Meadow Farm (Box 4, Item 106.1)
    - Never Touch Water (Box 4, Item 106.2)
    - Mon Petit Lapin (Box 4, Item 106.3)
    - Lord I've Got Some Singing to Do (Box 4, Item 106.4)
    - Red riding hood (Box 4, Item 106.5)
    - The Lonely Grenadier (Box 4, Item 106.6)
    - The Rambling River Line (Box 4, Item 106.7)
  - Broadway's Rotary Now! (Box 4, Folder 107)
    Music manuscript. Photostat Negative. 4 pages.
  - Chang Fu (Box 4, Folder 108)
    Music manuscript. Photostat negatives. 4 pages.
  - Get Your Glad Rags On (Box 4, Folder 109)
    Handwritten manuscript. Photostat negatives. 4 pages.
  - I Love You So (Box 4, Folder 110)
    Music manuscript. Photostat negatives. 3 pages.
  - I'm Going Back to My Baby Eskimo (Box 4, Folder 111)
    Music manuscript. Photostat Negatives. 4 pages.
  - In the Rain (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - My Lady Cloissone (Box 4, Folder 113)
    Music manuscript. Photostat negatives. 5 pages.
  - My Sweetheart Wears the Plaid (Box 4, Folder 114)
    Music manuscript. photostat negative. 3 page.
  - Open Up Those Doors of Delight (Box 4, Folder 116)
    Music manuscript. photostat negatives. 5 pages.
  - Winston, Franklin and Joe (Box 4, Folder 117)
    Music manuscript. Negative photostat. 3 pages.
  - 49 Angels (Box 4, Folder 122)
    typed manuscript with corrections.
  - I Remember You (Box 4, Folder 147)
    copy of manuscript (?) with penciled notations.
  - In Barcelona (Box 4, Folder 148)
    Music manuscript. Last page only.
  - In Barcelona (Box 4, Folder 149)
    Music manuscript. 1 page. Music by Carl Snyder. Words by Bob Schmertz.
  - Jonah, Jonah, Jonah (Box 4, Folder 150)
    Photostat of music manuscript. 3 pages.
  - Lord, Lord, I've Got Some Singing to Do (Box 4, Folder 152)
    copy of manuscript. Two pages.
  - General John Forbes (Box 6, Folder 176)
    Paste up of a manuscript for General Forbes.
  - Bushy Run (Box 6, Folder 177)
    Paste up of typed manuscript of Bushy Run.
  - The Ohio Company (Box 6, Folder 178)
    typed, pasted up manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Sing Oh! The City Oh! (Box 6, Folder 179)
    Pasted up typed manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Braddock's Defeat (Box 6, Folder 180)
    Typed, pasted up manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Singing Hallelujah! (Box 6, Folder 181)
    Typed pasted up manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Celeron (Box 6, Folder 182)
- Published Scores, IV.
  This series contains commercially published songs of Robert Schmertz and others.
  - Lord, Lord, I've Got Some Singin' To Do, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 151)
    Published score. 9 pages. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc. CM 7013. SATB with Piano. Two copies.
  - "Nile Song", 1919 (Box 5, Folder 153)
    Music by M. Rosenthal. Words by R. Schmertz. Published by W. R. Black, Jos. Cooney, 1919. 3 pages.
  - "Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord", 1951 (Box 5, Folder 154)
    Words and Music by Robert Schmertz. NY: Ludlow Music, Inc., 1951. Two pages.
  - "Noah (Noah Found Grace In the Eyes of the Lord)", 1951 (Box 5, Folder 155)
    Text and music by Robert Schmertz. Arranged by Thomas Gronau. German text by Ernst Bjelke. Published NY: Ludlow Music, 1951. 2 copies.
  - "Singing Halleluiah", 1953 (Box 5, Folder 157)
    For a chorus of mixed voices with piano. SATB. Words and music by Robert Schmertz. Arranged by Charles Touchette. Published by Carl Fischer, 1953. 7 pages.
  - "Soiree Charette Song Book" (Box 5, Folder 158)
    Two complete songs: "Nellie of Meadow Farm" and "The Lip that Touches Saxophones" words and music by Robert Schmertz. 3 pages. Two copies.
  - "Swing Away, Pearly Gates", 1954 (Box 5, Folder 159)
    Words and Music by Robert Schmertz. Arranged by Robert Schmertz for chorus of men's voices with baritone solo and piano. Published by Carl Fischer, 1954. 2 copies.
  - "Toka-San" (Box 5, Folder 160)
    Music by A. Herzberg, words by R. Schmertz. Published by W.R. Black and Jos. Cooney.
  - "Whimsical Women" (Box 5, Folder 161)
    Music by A. Schoepf. Words by R. Schmertz. No publisher info. 3 pages.
  - "Lord, Lord, I've Got Some Singing to Do", 1956 (Box 5, Folder 173)
    Tear sheet from book. Words and Music by Robert Schmertz. Published by Carl Fischer, Inc., 1956.
- Poems, V.
  This series contains manuscripts of poems written by Schmertz.
  - Poems (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - The Fellows Club (Box 4, Item 125.01)
      Typed manuscript with handwritten corrections. 1 page.
    - The Dismal Fate of Christopher Renfrew (Box 4, Item 125.02)
      Typed manuscript with handwritten notes. 2 pages.
    - Edward A. Wehr, Building 1878-1967 (Box 4, Item 125.03)
      Typed manuscript. 1 page.
    - An Air Raid Warden to His Lady (Box 4, Item 125.04)
      handwritten manuscript on lined paper.
    - The Wake of the W.P. Snyder, Jr. (Box 4, Item 125.05)
      Typed manuscript. 2 pages. Stapled.
    - On the Closing of the Anderson (Box 4, Item 125.06)
      handwritten manuscript. 3 pages.
    - [untitled], December 7, 1918 (Box 4, Item 125.07)
      Poem in letter format. handwritten front and back on lined paper.
    - In Saint Botoepls fair city (Box 4, Item 125.08)
      handwritten manuscript on lined paper. 1 page.
    - The Gentlemenly Members of the Fourth Estate (Box 4, Item 125.09)
      Typed manuscript on legal sized paper. 1 page.
    - Letter from Louis La Beaume to Robert Schmertz, November 5, 1946 (Box 4, Item 125.1)
      Letter to Schmertz congratulating on his poem honoring Christopher Renfew. 1 page on letterhead.
    - To Our First Born (Box 4, Item 125.11)
      Handwritten manuscript on lined yellow paper. 1 page.
    - Birthday Ballad for Bunny (or never mention a lady's age) (Box 4, Item 125.12)
      handwritten manuscript on 1 page. Upside down on letterhead.
    - For Mildred on Becoming a Registered Architect "In the Sovereign State of New York" (Box 4, Item 125.13)
      Typed manuscript on legal sized onion skin. 1 page.
    - Trinity Church Yard 1796-1942, October 1942 (Box 4, Item 125.14)
      Poem published in The Charette Volume XXII, No. 9. 1 page.
    - To a Departed Draftsman (Box 4, Item 125.15)
      typed manuscript with a handwritten note from "Steve."
    - The Molding, December 1956 (Box 4, Item 125.16)
      Tear sheet from Journal of the A.I.A. 4 pages.
    - Ode to the Ladies On the Occasion of the Book Club Meeting on March 15, 1958 (Box 4, Item 125.17)
      Typed manuscript with penciled corrections. 1 page.
    - Letter to Jackson (Box 4, Item 125.18)
      Letter to Jackson. handwritten 4 pages on lined yellow paper.
    - For Father Thomas Coakley (Box 4, Item 125.19)
    - To Haniel Long (Box 4, Item 125.2)
    - Lament, April 1955 (Box 4, Item 125.21)
      Tear sheet from Journal of the AIA. 4 pages.
    - Decentralize Organic'ly with Me (Box 4, Item 125.22)
    - My, My! What a Lovely Family! (Box 4, Item 125.23)
      handwritten manuscript on lined yellow paper. 5 pages.
    - Thoughts on the Palace at Knossos, November 1956 (Box 4, Item 125.24)
      Tear sheet from the Journal of the A.I.A. November 1956.
    - Thoughts on the Palace at Knossos after reading "Gods, Graves, and Scholars", March 1953 (Box 4, Item 125.25)
      Typed poem on onion skin with handwritten changes. 1/2 page.
    - To Ripley From Schmertz Ode to the Lally Column with object apologies to Ogden Nash (Box 4, Item 125.26)
      Tear sheet from the Charette.
    - Stones (Box 4, Item 125.27)
      Typed manuscript on Schmertz and Erwin letterhead. Title handwritten.
    - For Buela Russell, August 18, 1961 (Box 4, Item 125.28)
      Poem handwritten on Mrs. Robert W. Schmertz letterhead.
    - To George Howe (Box 4, Item 125.29)
      Mimeographed poem. 1 page.